Wilson, Ernest Henry, 1876-1930. Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952: Guide.
Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952.
Arnold Arboretum Archives of Harvard University, Jamaica Plain, MA 02130.
III EHW
Wilson, Ernest Henry, 1876-1930.
20 Linear Feet (30 Boxes)
The Ernest Henry Wilson Papers reflect his contribution to horticulture and botany as a plant collector who, through numerous expeditions to China, Korea, and Japan, introduced many new species into cultivation in arboreta, parks, and private gardens. The collection includes his extensive correspondence written between 1899 and 1930 to Arnold Arboretum staff, mainly Charles Sprague Sargent (1841-1927), the Arboretum's first director; copies of his letters to other Arboretum explorers and colleagues such as Joseph Charles Francis Rock (1884-1962), David Fairchild (1869-1954), Frank Nicholas Meyer (1875-1918) Alfred Rehder (1863-1949), and members of the Veitch Nurseries in England. Other material includes field and plant collection notes, diaries, account books, shipping lists, maps, and manuscripts of both published and unpublished works. There are Chinese and other travel documents, letters of recommendation, certificates and material relating to Wilson's life as a student and his early work as a gardener. There is an extensive collection of clippings from newspapers and copies of articles from botanical and horticultural journals. Material relating to the administration of Arnold Arboretum and his other activities at Harvard University are included, as well. Of special note is Wilson's photograph collection of approximately 7,700 images taken at the Arnold Arboretum, throughout New England, in Eastern Asia, and around the world.
Access to Finding Aid record in Hollis Classic or Hollis.
Current version of this finding aid is available at the Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University.
The following article, a copy of which was originally contained in Series IV, folder 4 (Plantings), can be found in Arnoldia: Wyman, Donald. “Plants for Screening Junkyards, Gravel Pits and Dumps.” Arnoldia 25, no. 8 (November 19, 1965): 45-48.
The following plans can be found in Drawer 5, folder 13A of the Arnold Arboretum Library map collection: 75% Submission—Plant and Path Layout/Grading Plan, Topographic Plan, Arnold Arboretum Expansion, prepared for Brown and Rowe, Inc. by Judith Nitsch Engineering, Inc. September 23, 1998.
Additional Ernest Henry Wilson correspondence can be found by searching the Arnold Arboretum Correspondence Index.
The major part of the E.H. Wilson collection has been at the Arnold Arboretum since Wilson's employment (1906-1930). The Veitch letters and many of the manuscripts were provided by his daughter, the late Muriel Primrose Wilson Slate (1906-1976), and her husband, Dr. George Slate (1899-1976) in 1952. Newspaper clipping and letters written by Wilson to his friend and nurseryman, Harlan Page Kelsey (1889–19? ) were presented to the Arnold Arboretum by his son, Seth Kelsey, in 1970. In 1981, Wilson's granddaughter, Mrs. John R. Abbott (Barbara Slate Abbott), gave additional documents and mementos to the archives. At that time some of the material contributed by Mrs. Abbott was transferred by Peter Shaw Ashton, the Arboretum's director, to the advocates of the creation of a museum dedicated to Wilson in Chipping Campden, England, and the present site of the E. H. Wilson Memorial Garden. Scheduled to open in 1984, the museum never materialized. In September 1996, the transferred papers and books were returned to the Arnold Arboretum from the Library of the Royal Botanic Garden, Kew where they had been on deposit. Wilson's letters to C.S. Sargent and the letters from Messrs. James Veitch and Sons, nurserymen, were included in the Wilson papers in 1984. In 1996, C.S. Sargent's letters to Wilson were removed from the Arboretum's Pre-1927 correspondence file and placed in the archives. Several of Wilson's notebooks which were originally catalogued and shelved in the library were moved to the archives in 1980. Parts of the Wilson papers were microfilmed in 1980: Harvard University Photographic Department. Microfilm: 80-3626. Master C804, Reel 3, 4.
Researchers seeking to examine archival materials are strongly encouraged to make an appointment. The Director, or an office of origin, may place restrictions on the use of some or all of its records. The extent and length of the restriction will be determined by the Director, office of origin, and the Archivist, and will be enforced equally for all researchers.
"Ernest Henry Wilson wished to go down in memory as 'Chinese Wilson,' and so it has been. His reputation today is certainly that of one of the most successful individuals to introduce horticulturally valuable plants from China to western gardens. Over 1,000 different plants were gathered by Wilson and introduced in England and America as seeds, bulbs, cuttings, or plants; these have since become established in the horticultural trade and in private or botanical gardens."
Introduction to "E.H. Wilson as a Botanist," by Richard A. Howard, Director, Arnold Arboretum Arnoldia, 40; 3, 4, 1980.
E. H. Wilson was born at Chipping Campden, Gloucestershire, England, on February 15, 1876, the eldest of Henry and Annie (Curtis) Wilson's seven children. On leaving school, Wilson apprenticed at the nurseries of Messrs. Hewitt of Solihull, Warwickshire. In 1892, at sixteen, he was employed at the Birmingham Botanical Gardens as a gardener and, on his own time in the evening, studied botany at the Birmingham Technical School. His next employment, which began in January 1897, was at the Royal Botanic Garden, Kew. In October of the following year, Wilson began studies at the Royal College of Science in South Kensington.
When the nursery firm of Veitch and Sons asked William Turner Thiselton-Dyer (1843-1928), the director of the Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew (1885-1891), to recommend a suitable man to be sent to China to collect seeds and plants, it was the young E.H. Wilson he nominated. After six months of training under George Harrow at Veitch's Coombe Wood Nursery, Wilson left for China in 1899 and began a successful career in introducing Asiatic plants to the West. On his way to China, he visited at the Arnold Arboretum for five days, and initiated a life-long collaboration with the institution. In April 1902, Wilson returned to England and on June 8, 1902 married Ellen Ganderton of Edgbaston, Warwickshire. They had one daughter, Muriel Primrose, who would later marry the American botanist, George Slate, a plant breeder at the Agricultural Experiment Station in Geneva, New York. Wilson went on a second trip to China for Veitch that lasted from 1903 to 1906. For the remainder of 1906, he worked as an assistant at the Imperial Institute, London.
His third and fourth China expeditions (1906-1911) were arranged by C.S. Sargent under the sponsorship of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University. "A good set of photographs are really about as important as anything you can bring back with you," Sargent wrote as he prepared for his first Arboretum-sponsored expedition. Sargent insisted Wilson take on this journey and on all that would follow, a large format Sanderson whole-plate field camera capable of recording both great detail and broad perspectives without distortion. For three years, beginning in late 1906, Wilson explored western Hupeh and western Szechuan. He arrived in Boston in 1909 via Beijing, Moscow, St. Petersburg, Berlin, Paris, and finally London, where he spent several months developing the glass-plate negatives and seeing his 720 images for the first time. Also in 1909, the family moved to Boston; Ernest and Ellen Wilson would eventually live in a house constructed for them on the grounds of the Arboretum, where they would make their home for the rest of their lives.
The purpose of his second Arboretum expedition, which began in 1910, was to collect cones and conifer seeds in the central and southwestern parts of China. In September of that year, while traveling between Sungpan and Chentu, a landslide hit the expedition group, crushing Wilson's leg. After several months in a hospital at Chentu, Wilson returned to Boston in March 1911, much earlier than planned. Before the accident, however, he had managed to take 374 images and to collect and ship bulbs of Lilium regale, the Easter Lily, to Boston.
In January 1914, accompanied by his wife and daughter, Wilson sailed for Japan, where he would focus his attention on cultivated plants, horticulture, conifers, Kurume azaleas, and Japanese cherries. By the time the Wilsons returned to Boston at the beginning of 1915, there were 619 new images to add to the photograph collection. Wilson next undertook a "systematic exploration" of the region in 1917 and travelled to the Bonin Islands, Japan, Formosa, and along the Yalu River into the far northern reaches of Korea, returning to Boston in 1919 with seeds, living plants, 30,000 herbarium specimens, and 700 photographs. His last expedition, a tour of the gardens of the world, took place from 1920 to 1922 and included, in alphabetical order: Australia, England, France, India, Kenya, New Zealand, Pakistan, Singapore, South Africa, and Tasmania.
In addition to being a plant explorer and a botanist, Wilson became a prolific author and a much sought-after lecturer. His articles appeared in the popular press as well as in the botanical literature, and he often illustrated his talks with hand-colored lantern slides adapted from the glass plate negatives created during his travels. In 1919, Wilson was appointed Assistant Director; after Sargent's death in 1927, Wilson became "Keeper" of the Arnold Arboretum. Three years later, his remarkable career was cut short when he and his wife were killed in an automobile accident on October 15, 1930 outside Worcester, Massachusetts. Ernest and Ellen Wilson are buried in the Mont-Royal Cemetery in Montreal, Canada.
Scope and Content Note
Although there are a small number of personal family photographs in the collection, no family papers or family correspondence appear to exist. The first trip to China for Messrs. Veitch is the least documented expedition in the collection. No diary from this trip has been found, although evidence indicates that a diary was kept. No letters from Wilson to the Veitch firm have been located from the expeditions for Messrs. Veitch. However, the Veitch's letters to Wilson, as well as their instructions to him for both trips, are included.
His papers also include some early work and education records, diaries, field and plant notes, account books, shipping lists, maps, Chinese and other travel documents, manuscripts, clippings, and several hundred letters to and from Wilson. Also included in his archives is an extensive and virtually complete collection of Wilson's photographs, lantern slides, and glass plate negatives. Some references to photography can be found in the notebooks, but no separate photography notebook exists.
Also in the collection are contemporary articles and books about Wilson, records pertaining to exhibits of Wilson material, and correspondence relating to the Arboretum's archival holdings.
Appendix 1 holds two earlier drafts of the finding aid for the Ernest Henry Wilson Papers, from 1984 and 1997. The 1984 document is the first finding aid created by the Archives of the Arnold Arboretum Library.
Series and Subseries Arrangement
Series I
Subseries A
Group 1
Group 2
Group 3
Group 4
Subseries B
Group B1
Group B2
Group B3
Group B4
Subseries C
Group C1
Group C2
Sub-group C2a
Sub-group C2b
Sub-group C2c
Subseries D
Series II
Subseries II A
Group II 1
Group II 2
Group II 3
Group II 4
Subseries II B
Subseries II C
Subseries II D
Series III
For additional information about E.H. Wilson published by the Arnold Arboretum, see:
Chvany, Peter J. "E. H. Wilson, Photographer." Arnoldia, 36:5 (1976).
Clausen, Kristen; Hu, Shiu-ying. "Mapping the Collecting Localities of E. H. Wilson in China." Arnoldia, 40:3 (1980).
Ferguson, A.R. "E. H. Wilson, Yichang, and the Kiwifruit." Arnoldia, 43:4 (1983).
Gardner, William. "E. H. Wilson's First Trip to China." Arnoldia, 32:3 (1972).
Howard, Richard A. "E. H. Wilson as a Botanist (Part I)." Arnoldia, 40:3 (1980).
Howard, Richard A. "E. H. Wilson as a Botanist (Part II)." Arnoldia, 40:4 (1980).
For an online exhibit of the Wilson Collection, please visit the Open Collections Program webpage at http://ocp.hul.harvard.edu/expeditions/wilson_records.html.
- W.I: Biographical Material
  This series is divided into five subseries: A-E
  - Subseries W.I:A: The Early Working Years in England, 1896-1898.
    - Box 1
      - Folder 1
        - Letter of recommendation on behalf of EHW, signed by W. Spinks, manager of Hewitt & Co., a nursery at Edgbaston, Birmingham, England. Dated August 20,1896.
      - Folder 2
        - Letter of recommendation on behalf of EHW, signed by W.B. Latham, curator at the Botanical Gardens, Edgbaston, Birmingham, England. Dated August 17, 1896.
      - Folder 3
        - Letter of recommendation on behalf of EHW, signed by Joseph W. Oliver, Municipal Technical School, Birmingham, England. Dated August 20, 1896.
      - Folder 4
        - Certificate of work at Royal Gardens, Kew, England, January 4, 1897 to October 1, 1898, and signed October 1, 1898, by Director Dyer and Curator Nicholson.
      - Folder 5
        - Examination in Botany, London, 1898.
      - Folder 6
        - List of candidates who were successful in their examination, 1898. Dept. of Science and Art of the Committee of Council on Education. EHW's name listed.
      - Folder 7
        - Certificate of courses taken by EHW, while employed in the Royal Gardens, Kew, October 1, 1898.
      - Folder 8
        - Printed Rules and Regulations for Workmen. Royal Garden, Kew, 1895.
      - Folder 9
        - Letter of recommendation on behalf of EHW, signed by Wyndham Dunhan, Imperial Institute, London, S. W. Dated November 16, 1906.
  - Subseries W.I:B: Harvard Employment Documents
    - Box 1
      - Folder 10
        - Certificate of EHW's employment as an Assistant at the Arnold Arboretum, 1915.
      - Folder 11
        - Similar certificate for 1916.
      - Folder 12
        - Similar certificate for 1917 and Assistant Director, 1919.
      - Folder 13
        - Salary notice to EHW from the Harvard College Bursar's office, 1918.
      - Folder 14
        - Similar notice for 1919.
  - Subseries W.I:C: Personal Legal Documents
    - Box 1
      - Folder 15
        - Copy of EHW's will.
        - EHW and Ellen Wilson's marriage certificate, 1902.
        - EHW and Ellen Wilson's joint passport.
        - Muriel Wilson's passport.
      - Folder 16
        - Passenger records for EHW's arrival at Ellis Island on December 14, 1906 and on August 24, 1911. (Printouts from www.ellisislandrecords.org)
  - Subseries W.I:D: Awards, Certificates, Honors and Oversized Materials
    - Box 2: Oversized Materials
      - Folder 1: Photographs of awards
        - The tie pin presented to EHW by the Veitch firm after the second expedition to China. The pin represents Meconopsis integrifolia with gold petals and forty diamonds for stamens. (2 different photographs)
        - The pocket watch presented to EHW inscribed "With Best Wishes of The Horticultural Club of Boston" January 1914. "E.H. Wilson from James H. Veitch 1899-1902 Well Done!" (2 different photographs)
      - Folder 2
        - Shirley C.E. Schools' certificates for the years 1883-1887, 1889.
        - Shirley C.E. Schools' Certificate of merit, 6th standard, 1888.
        - Good conduct and proficiency certificate in religion, 1889.
        - Good conduct and proficiency certificate in arithmetic, 1889.
        - Certificate of passage of 1st class, advanced stage, botany, 1896.
        - Certificate of passage of examination in horticulture, 1st class, higher grade.
        - Certificate of honors in botany, 1898.
        - Certificate for the Victoria Medal of Honour issued by the Royal Horticultural Society, 1912.
        - Letter from Privy Purse Office, Buckingham Palace, thanking EHW for donation of book, Arnold Arboretum, 1926.
        - Honorary membership in Worcester County Horticultural Society, 1927.
        - Photograph of the Loder Rhododendron Cup Award, EHW, 1927.
        - Certificate of Fellow of American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1929.
        - Vote of thanks certificate from Massachusetts Horticultural Society for help in Centennial Exhibition, 1929.
        - Honorary doctorate, Trinity College, 1930. In Latin.
        - Honorary membership in American Orchid Society.
        - Printed replicas of medals received by EHW.
      - Box 2: Loose Materials
        - Certificate of passage of elementary stage of botany, 1895.
        - Certificate of corresponding membership in Massachusetts Horticultural Society, 1911.
        - Certificate of Life Membership in Massachusetts Horticultural Society, 1915.
        - Certificate for grand medal of Société Nationale d'Acclimatation of France, 1918.
        - Life membership certificate in American Rose Society, 1923.
    - Box 3
      - 1. The tie pin presented to EHW by the Veitch firm after the second expedition to China, 1905.
      - 2. Medal: Royal Horticultural Society. "To the Harvard University for photographs of expedition to China by E. H. Wilson, August 1909."
      - 3. Medal: Massachusetts Horticultural Society. Awarded to EHW for photographs illustrating his plant collecting expeditions in China, January 1910.
      - 4. Royal Horticultural Society. Victoria Medal, 1912.
      - 5. Medal: Massachusetts Horticultural Society. Awarded to EHW in further recognition of his eminent service to horticulture, 1912.
      - 6. George Robert White Medal of Honor. Massachusetts Horticultural Society Award to EHW MCMXV for eminent service in Horticulture.
      - 7. Medal: Iside Geoffroy St. Hilaire. Société Nationale d'Acclimatation de France. EHW, 1918.
      - 8. Medal: Massachusetts Horticultural Society. Awarded to EHW. For Introduction of Kurume Azaleas, March 1920.
      - 9. The Veitch Memorial Medal. "Mr. E. H. Wilson. For his introductions to gardens and his books. 1926."
      - 10. Medal: Massachusetts Horticultural Society. Centennial 1929. EHW for inspirational books.
      - 11. Massachusetts Horticultural Society. Centennial 1929. Award to EHW. For a planting of Lilium Regale. 1929.
      - 12. In the exhibit hall. The Veitch Memorial Medal. Presented to Wilson in recognition of his great services to horticulture by the discovery and introduction of new plants from China. 1906. The other is: Awarded to Ernest H. Wilson in appreciation of the discovery and introduction of the Regal Lily and the many other outstanding and valuable plants from China.
  - Subseries W.I:E: Photographs
    - Box 1
      - Folder 17: Portraits of Ernest Henry Wilson
        - Earliest known photograph of EHW. Taken at Birmingham Botanical Gardens, Edgbaston, 1894. (1 photograph)
        - Portrait of EHW as a young man, Birmingham, no date. (1 photograph)
        - Portrait of EHW, Hong Kong. (1 photograph)
        - Portrait of EHW, used as a publicity photograph, taken in 1921. (18 photographs and 1 slide)
        - EHW standing on the steps of the Hunnewell Building of the Arnold Arboretum, September 25, 1922. (16 photographs and 2 negatives)
        - EHW sitting on the steps of the Hunnewell Building of the Arnold Arboretum, September 25, 1922. (6 photographs—one is cropped and one negative)
        - EHW in garden at home at 380 South Street, Jamaica Plain, MA, holding a cigar, September, 1924. (2 different photographs)
        - EHW looking at the Cornus kousa chinenis in the Arnold Arboretum, 1924.
        - EHW in the Arnold Arboretum Reading Room, Hunnewell Building, November 5, 1924. (2 different photographs (3 copies of one))
        - EHW, Botanist and Keeper of the Arnold Arboretum, no date. (1 photograph)
        - EHW sitting on a fence, no date. (1 photograph)
        - EHW standing on a road, no date. (1 photograph)
        - EHW, President of Horticultural Club of Boston, 1927?
        - EHW at the Arnold Arboretum, 1929?
        - EHW in cap and gown, seated among the lilies of South Street garden after receiving his honorary doctorate from Trinity College, 1930. (10 photographs and 2 negatives)
        - Sketch of EHW by Pamela Bruns, no date. (1 drawing and 1 negative with display card.)
        - Correspondence and other documentation concerning EHW portrait painted by Mrs. G.C. Page in 1933. Painting on loan from the Massachusetts Horticultural Society, hanging on the 4th floor Hunnewell Building, 2009.
      - Folder 18: Ernest Henry Wilson Family Photographs
        - Muriel Wilson, age 5, next to Vitus labrusia growing in the original Arnold Arboretum shrub collection, circa 1908. (1 photograph)
        - EHW, Ellen Wilson, and Muriel family portrait taken in Tokyo, 1914. (6 photographs, 3 negatives)
        - "Yours Truly Mu," Woking, England, 1923. (1 photograph)
        - "Our first car, Jewell, taken at Arnold Arboretum," with Ellen Wilson, Minnie Prevost, and Aunt Betty, 1923. (1 photograph)
        - Aunt Betty outside 380 South Street, Jamaica Plain, MA. (1 photograph)
        - Ellen Wilson, Aunt Betty Mumford (Collins), and Muriel at 380 South Street, Jamaica Plain, MA. (2 photographs)
        - EHW and Muriel with family dog on a picnic in Canada. (2 photographs)
        - EHW, Ellen Wilson, Muriel, and Betty Mumford near Willoughby Lake, VT. (2 photographs)
        - EHW, Muriel and unknown man near Willoughby Lake, VT. (2 photographs)
        - Aunt May (Wilson) (Mrs. Butter). (1 photograph)
        - Aunt Flo (Wilson) (Mrs. Furland). (1 photograph)
        - EHW's granddaughter Barbara Abbott at Arnold Arboretum standing steps of the Hunnewell Building. Posed as the 1922 EHW photograph. (2 photographs)
      - Folder 19: Photographs of Ernest Henry Wilson Friends and Associates
        - "Bothy" crew at Royal Botanical Gardens Kew. (1 photograph)
          NOTE: Royal Botanical Gardens Kew states that "This photograph has been examined by several Kew staff and we do not think it was taken at Kew."
        - EHW and Professor Charles Sprague Sargent standing in front of the Prunus subhirtella, May 2, 1915. (2 photographs)
        - C.W. Hoitt, Judge of Supreme Court of New Hampshire, December 24, 1920. (1 photograph)
        - EHW and R. Kanakawa outside the Hunnewell Building, March 19, 1929. (1 photograph)
        - EHW and Fred Landis at the Arnold Arboretum, July 1929. (1 photograph)
        - Thomas Roland Memoriam with photograph, 1863-1929, by Walter Gardner Kendall. (1 photograph)
        - T. Howard Stewart in Montreal. Died September 1951 at the age of 82. Close friend of EHW. (1 photograph)
      - Folder 20: Photographs relating to Wilson's birthplace and Memorials
        - EHW's birthplace Chipping Campden, England. (2 different photographs—one from W.H. Judd, January 15, 1936; the other by Stephen A. Spongberg, no date)
        - E.H. Wilson's birthplace, Chipping Campden, England. Photographs gift of his nephew, Roy Briggs, 1989. (16 photographs, includes some of the memorial garden)
        - The parish church of St. Georges Edgbaston where Ellen "Nellie" Ganderton and EHW wed on June 8, 1902. (2 photographs—one from Roy Briggs.)
        - Ernest Henry Wilson Monument in Mont-Royal Cemetery, Montreal. (No mention of Ellen Wilson on stone. S. Connor) (1 photograph)
        - Ernest Henry Wilson memorial garden in Chipping Campden, England. (1 photograph)
        - Unidentified ship. (1 photograph)
  - Subseries W.I:F: Family and Friends Documents
    - Box 1
      - Folder 21 Collins, Elizabeth M.